On March 10, 2011,
في العاشر من مارس عام ٢٠١١
I was in Cambridge at the MIT Media Lab
كنت في كامبردج في معمل معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية
meeting with faculty, students and staff,
حيث اجتمعت بهيئة التدريس والطلبة وباقي الموظفين
and we were trying to figure out whether
كنا نحاول أن نعرف
I should be the next director.
ما إذا كان عليّ أن أكون المدير القادم
That night, at midnight,
في تلك الليلة، في منتصف الليل
a magnitude 9 earthquake
ضربت هزة أرضية بمقياس ٩
hit off of the Pacific coast of Japan.
ساحل اليابان المقابل للمحيط الهادي
My wife and family were in Japan,
كانت زوجتي وعائلتي هناك في اليابان
and as the news started to come in,
وما أن بدأت الأخبار تتواتر
I was panicking.
كنت مذعوراً
I was looking at the news streams
كنت أقرأ شريط الأخبار
and listening to the press conferences
واستمع للمؤتمرات الصحفية
of the government officials
للمسؤولين الحكوميين
and the Tokyo Power Company,
وشركة طوكيو للطاقة
and hearing about this explosion
وأسمع عن الانفجار
at the nuclear reactors
في المفاعلات النووية
and this cloud of fallout
وتلك السحابة من الجزيئات المشعة
that was headed towards our house
التي كانت متجهة نحو منزلنا
which was only about 200 kilometers away.
والذي كان يبعد حوالي ٢٠٠ كيلومتر فقط
And the people on TV weren't telling us
ولم يكن الأشخاص في التلفاز يطلعوننا
anything that we wanted to hear.
عما نحتاج لمعرفته
I wanted to know what was going on with the reactor,
أردت أن أعرف ماذا يحدث بالنسبة للمفاعل
what was going on with the radiation,
ماذا بالنسبة للإشعاعات
whether my family was in danger.
هل عائلتي بخطر؟
So I did what instinctively felt like the right thing,
لذلك قمت وقتها بما أحسست أنه صائب
which was to go onto the Internet
توجهت للإنترنت
and try to figure out
وحاولت أن أعرف
if I could take matters into my own hands.
اذا كنت استطيع أن آخذ زمام الأمور بنفسي
On the Net, I found there were a lot of other people
وجدت الكثير من الأشخاص على الشبكة
like me trying to figure out what was going on,
يحاولون مثلي معرفة ما يحدث
and together we sort of loosely formed a group
قمنا تقريبًا بتشكيل مجموعة
and we called it Safecast,
حيث أطلقنا عليها البثّ الآمن
and we decided we were going to try
وقررنا أننا سنحاول
to measure the radiation
قياس الإشعاعات
and get the data out to everybody else,
ونشر تلك البيانات للجميع
because it was clear that the government
لأنه كان من الواضح أن الحكومة
wasn't going to be doing this for us.
لن تقوم بذلك من أجلنا
Three years later,
وبعد ثلاث سنوات
we have 16 million data points,
أصبح لدينا ١٦ مليون نقطة بيانات
we have designed our own Geiger counters
صممنا عدادات (غايغر) خاصة بنا
that you can download the designs
حيث تستطيع تحميل التصميم
and plug it into the network.
وإيصاله بالشبكة
We have an app that shows you
لدينا تطبيق يظهر لك
most of the radiation in Japan and other parts of the world.
أغلب الإشعاعات في اليابان وأجزاء آخرى من العالم
We are arguably one of the most successful
يمكن القول بأننا أنجح
citizen science projects in the world,
فريق من المواطنين على مستوى العالم
and we have created
وقمنا بإنشاء
the largest open dataset of radiation measurements.
أكبر قاعدة بيانات مفتوحة لقياس الإشعاعات
And the interesting thing here
والمثير للإهتمام هنا
is how did — (Applause) — Thank you.
هو كيف أن-(تصفيق)- شكراً لكم
How did a bunch of amateurs
كيف أن مجموعة من الهواة
who really didn't know what we were doing
الذين لا يعرفون شيء عما نفعله
somehow come together
بشكل ما اجتمعوا سوياً
and do what NGOs and the government
وفعلوا ما لم تستطع المنظمات
were completely incapable of doing?
الحكومية والخاصة من فعله؟
And I would suggest that this has something to do
وأود أن أشير أن لذلك علاقة
with the Internet. It's not a fluke.
بالإنترنت فلم يكن ذلك عفوياً
It wasn't luck, and it wasn't because it was us.
لم يكن ذلك حظاً، ولم يكن بسببنا نحن
It helped that it was an event
ما ساعد هو وجود حدث
that pulled everybody together,
جمع الكل مع بعضهم
but it was a new way of doing things
لكنها كانت طريقة جديدة للعمل
that was enabled by the Internet
فعّلها وجود الإنترنت
and a lot of the other things that were going on,
والمزيد من الأمور التي كانت تحدث
and I want to talk a little bit about
أريد التحدث قليلاً عن
what those new principles are.
ماهية تلك المبادئ الجديدة
So remember before the Internet? (Laughter)
اتذكرون وقت ما قبل الانترنت ؟ (ضحك)
I call this B.I. Okay?
سأدعوها ق.إ. موافقون؟
So, in B.I., life was simple.
كانت الحياة ماقبل الإنترنت بسيطة
Things were Euclidian, Newtonian,
كانت الأشياء إقليدية ونيوتيونية
somewhat predictable.
متوقعة إلى حد ما
People actually tried to predict the future,
حاول الناس توقع المستقبل،
even the economists.
حتى الإقتصاديون حاولوا القيام بذلك.
And then the Internet happened,
وبعدها أتى الإنترنت
and the world became extremely complex,
فأصبح العالم معقدًا جدًا
extremely low-cost, extremely fast,
منخفض التكلفة وسريعًا جداً
and those Newtonian laws
وأصبحت قوانين نيوتن
that we so dearly cherished
تلك العزيزة علينا
turned out to be just local ordinances,
مجرد أمور محلية فقط
and what we found was that in this
والذي اكتشفناه في هذا
completely unpredictable world
العالم الذي لايمكن التنبؤ به أبداً
that most of the people who were surviving
هو أن الأشخاص الذين يحاولون العيش
were working with sort of a different set of principles,
كانوا يعملون وفق مجموعة مختلفة من المبادئ
and I want to talk a little bit about that.
وأريد التحدث قليلاً عن ذلك.
Before the Internet, if you remember,
قبل الإنترنت لو تتذكرون
when we tried to create services,
عندما كنا نريد إنشاء خدمات
what you would do is you'd create
فإن ما نفعله هو إنشاء
the hardware layer and the network layer and the software
طبقة الأجهزة والشبكة والبرامج
and it would cost millions of dollars
وسيكلف ذلك ملايين الدولارات
to do anything that was substantial.
لعمل أي شيء رئيسي
So when it costs millions of dollars to do something substantial,
لذا فحين يكلفك عمل شيء رئيسي ملايين الدولارات
what you would do is you'd get an MBA
عندها قد تستعين بمن لديه شهادة إدارة أعمال
who would write a plan
ليضع لك خطة
and get the money
ثم يحصل على النقود
from V.C.s or big companies,
من رأس مال استثماري أو شركات كبرى
and then you'd hire the designers and the engineers,
بعدها تستأجر المصممين والمهندسين
and they'd build the thing.
ويقومون ببناء ذلك الشيء
This is the Before Internet, B.I., innovation model.
هذا نموذج الابتكار ماقبل الإنترنت
What happened after the Internet was
ماحدث بعد ظهور الإنترنت هو
the cost of innovation went down so much
أن تكلفة الابتكار انخفضت بشكل كبير
because the cost of collaboration, the cost of distribution,
بسبب أن تكلفة التعاون وتكلفة التوزيع
the cost of communication, and Moore's Law
وتكلفة التواصل وقانون "مور"
made it so that the cost of trying a new thing
جعل من تكلفة تجربة شيء جديد
became nearly zero,
تساوي الصفر تقريبًا
and so you would have Google, Facebook, Yahoo,
بعدها سيقوم طلاب من غوغل وفيسبوك وياهو
students that didn't have permission —
طلاب ليس لديهم ترخيص--
permissionless innovation —
ليس لديهم ترخيص للاختراع--
didn't have permission, didn't have PowerPoints,
ليس لديهم رخصة ولا وسائل عرض
they just built the thing,
فقط يقومون بتصمم ماتريده
then they raised the money,
بعدها يوفرون التمويل
and then they sort of figured out a business plan
وبطريقة ما يستنتجون خطة عمل
and maybe later on they hired some MBAs.
لاحقاً قد يستأجرون من يحملون شهادة إدارة أعمال
So the Internet caused innovation,
بالتالي فإن الإنترنت أدى إلى الإبتكار
at least in software and services,
على الأقل في البرامج والخدمات
to go from an MBA-driven innovation model
للانتقال من نموذج الابتكار المدعوم بإدارة الإعمال
to a designer-engineer-driven innovation model,
إلى نموذج الابتكار المدعوم بالتصميم الهندسي
and it pushed innovation to the edges,
وقد دفع ذلك بالابتكار إلى القمة،
to the dorm rooms, to the startups,
إلى غرف النوم وإلى الشركات الناشئة
away from the large institutions,
بعيدًا عن المؤسسات الكبرى
the stodgy old institutions that had the power
القديمة والمملة والتي تملك القوة
and the money and the authority.
والمال والسلطة
And we all know this. We all know this happened on the Internet.
ونعرف كلناهذا .ان هذا يحدث على الانترنت
It turns out it's happening in other things, too.
وقد اتضح أن ذلك يحدث في أمور أخرى أيضاً
Let me give you some examples.
دعوني أعطيكم بعض الأمثلة
So at the Media Lab, we don't just do hardware.
في مختبر الميديا لا نعمل فقط على الأجهزة
We do all kinds of things.
نحن نقوم بكل الأشياء
We do biology, we do hardware,
نعمل على الأحياء والأجهزة
and Nicholas Negroponte famously said, "Demo or die,"
قال نيكولاس نيقروبنتي عبارته المشهورة "جرب أو مت"
which was the traditional academic way of thinking.
والتي كانت الطريقة التعليمية التقليدية في التفكير
And he often said, the demo only has to work once,
وغالبًا ما يقول: يعمل النموذج التجريبي لمرة فقط
because the primary mode of us impacting the world
ولأن النموذج الأولي منا أثر على العالم
was through large companies
عن طريق شركات كبرى
being inspired by us
التي استلهمت أفكارها منا
and creating products like the Kindle or Lego Mindstorms.
وصممت منتجات مثل كيندل وليقو
But today, with the ability
لكن اليوم ومع القدرة
to deploy things into the real world at such low cost,
على توزيع الأشياء في العالم بسعر منخفض
I'm changing the motto now,
سأقوم بتغيير الشعار الآن
and this is the official public statement.
وهذا يعتبر تصريح شعبي رسمي
I'm officially saying, "Deploy or die."
أقول وبرسمية، "وزّع أو مت"
You have to get the stuff into the real world
عليك أن تنقل الأشياء للعالم الواقعي.
for it to really count,
ليكون لها معنى،
and sometimes it will be large companies,
و أحياناً ستصبح شركات كبرى
and Nicholas can talk about satellites.
يمكن لنيكولاس أن يتحدث عن الأقمار الصناعية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً
But we should be getting out there ourselves
لكن يجب أن نُخرج أنفسنا من هناك
and not depending on large institutions to do it for us.
وأن لا نعتمد على المؤسسات الكبرى للقيام بذلك بدلا عنا.
So last year, we sent a bunch of students to Shenzhen,
قبل عام أرسلنا مجموعة من الطلاب إلى مدينة شنجن
and they sat on the factory floors
وجلسوا عن الأرض المصنع
with the innovators in Shenzhen, and it was amazing.
مع المبتكرين في شنتشن و كان مدهش
What was happening there
ما كان يحدث هناك
was you would have these manufacturing devices,
هو قدرتك على تصنيع الأجهزة,
and they weren't making prototypes or PowerPoints.
ولم يقع وضع نماذج ولا شرائح عرض.
They were fiddling with the manufacturing equipment
كانوا يتلاعبون بمعدات التصنيع
and innovating right on the manufacturing equipment.
والابتكار مباشرة باعتماد معدات التصنيع
The factory was in the designer,
كان المصنع المصمم
and the designer was literally in the factory.
و المصمم كان حرفيا في المصنع
And so what you would do is,
و ما كنت ستفعله هو
you'd go down to the stalls
زيارة قاعات عرض السلع والمحلات
and you would see these cell phones.
ورؤية هذه الهواتف المحمولة
So instead of starting little websites
والتالي بدلا من البدء صغارا بالمواقع
like the kids in Palo Alto do,
مثلما يفعل الأطفال في بالو ألتو،
the kids in Shenzhen make new cell phones.
يصنع الأطفال في شنتشن هواتف جديدة
They make new cell phones like kids in Palo Alto
يصنعون الهواتف المحمولة الجديدة مثل الأطفال في بالوألتو
make websites,
يقومون ببناء المواقع على الانترنت،
and so there's a rainforest
وبالتالي يوجد تنوع وكثرة
of innovation going on in the cell phone.
الابتكارات المتواصلة فيما يتعلق بالهواتف.
What they do is, they make a cell phone,
ما يقومون به، هو صنع هاتف خلوي،
go down to the stall, they sell some,
ثم يعرضونه في المحلات ويبيعونها.
they look at the other kids' stuff, go up,
يلقون نظرة على هواتف الآخرين ثم يعدون إلى المنزل
make a couple thousand more, go down.
يقومون بصنع بضعة آلاف آخرى، ثم يعرضونها.
Doesn't this sound like a software thing?
ألا يبدو هذا مثل البرمجيات؟
It sounds like agile software development,
يبدو أن كتطوير البرمجيات أجيل
A/B testing and iteration,
أ/ب التجربة و التكرار،
and what we thought you could only do with software
وما إعتقدنا أنه يمكن فقط فعله في البرمجيات
kids in Shenzhen are doing this in hardware.
يقوم الاطفال فى شنتشن بعمله في الأجهزة.
My next fellow, I hope, is going to be
أرجو أن يكون زميلي القادم
one of these innovators from Shenzhen.
واحد من هؤلاء المخترعين من شنتشن
And so what you see is
وبالتالي ما تلاحظه هو
that is pushing innovation to the edges.
أنه وقع دفع الابتكار إلى حدوده.
We talk about 3D printers and stuff like that,
نتحدث عن آلات طباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد وأشياء من هذا القبيل
and that's great, but this is Limor.
وهذا جيد، لكن أعرفكم على ليمور
She is one of our favorite graduates,
وهي واحدة من أحسن الخريجين.
and she is standing in front of a Samsung
وتقف أمام آلة من سامسونج
Techwin Pick and Place Machine.
لتجميع وتركيب المكونات الصغيرة في الهاتف النقال.
This thing can put 23,000 components per hour
يمكن لهذا آلة تجميع 23.000 مكون في الساعة
onto an electronics board.
على لوحة إلكترونية
This is a factory in a box.
هذا مصنع في شكل صندوق.
So what used to take a factory full of workers
إذن ما إعتاد مصنع مليء بالعمال
working by hand
يعملون بأيديهم
in this little box in New York,
في هذه العلبة في نيويورك
she's able to have effectively —
يمكن أن تكون فعالةَ --
She doesn't actually have to go to Shenzhen
لا يجب عليك الذهاب الى شنتشن
to do this manufacturing.
للقيام بعملية التصنيع
She can buy this box and she can manufacture it.
يمكنها شراء هذه الآلة والبدء بتصنيعه.
So manufacturing, the cost of innovation,
لذلك عملية التصنيع وتكلفة الابتكار،
the cost of prototyping, distribution, manufacturing, hardware,
وتكلفة صنع النماذج والتوزيع وتصنيع والأجهزة
is getting so low
أصبحت أرخص.
that innovation is being pushed to the edges
وقد دفع لابتكار لأقصاه
and students and startups are being able to build it.
فأصبح الطلاب والشركات الناشئة قادرين على صنعها
This is a recent thing, but this will happen
هذه آخر المستجدات، ولكن هذا سيحدث
and this will change
وسيتغير هذا
just like it did with software.
مثلما حدث مع البرمجيات
Sorona is a DuPont process
تعتبر سورانا نهجا من الأنهج التي تعتمدها شركة دوبونت
that uses a genetically engineered microbe
والتي تستعمل جرثومة معدلة من حيث الهندسة الوراثية
to turn corn sugar into polyester.
تقوم بتحويل سكر الذرة إلى قطن
It's 30 percent more efficient than the fossil fuel method,
والتي تعتبر 30 في المئة أكثر كفاءة من الوقود الأحفوري
and it's much better for the environment.
وهي أفضل بكثير للبيئة.
Genetic engineering and bioengineering
قامت الهندسة الوراثية والهندسة الحيوية
are creating a whole bunch
بإنشاء مجموعة كاملة من
of great new opportunities
الفرص الجديدة والرائعة
for chemistry, for computation, for memory.
للكيمياء والعمليات الحسابية والذاكرة.
We will probably be doing a lot, obviously doing health things,
من المحتمل أن نقوم بعمل الكثير، من الجلي القيام بأمور سليمة
but we will probably be growing chairs
لكن من المحتمل أن نقوم بتكوين فروع
and buildings soon.
ومباني، قريبا.
The problem is, Sorona costs about 400 million dollars
تكمن المشكلة في أن تكلفة تبلغ حوالي 400 مليون دولار
and took seven years to build.
وتحتاج 7 سنوات لتكوينها.
It kind of reminds you of the old mainframe days.
يذكرك هذا نوعا ما بالأيام القديمة
The thing is, the cost of innovation
يكمن الأمر في أن تكلفة الإبتكار
in bioengineering is also going down.
في الهندسة الحيوية ينخفض.
This is desktop gene sequencer.
على سطح هذا المكتب توجد آلة التسلسل الجيني.
It used to cost millions and millions of dollars to sequence genes.
كانت القيام بعملية التسلسل الجيني يكلف الملايين من الدولارات
Now you can do it on a desktop like this,
أما الآن فقط أصبح من الممكن أن تقوم بها على حاسوب مثل هذا
and kids can do this in dorm rooms.
ويمكن للأطفال القيام بذلك من مساكنهم
This is Gen9 gene assembler,
هذه "Gen9" المجمع الجيني
and so right now when you try to print a gene,
وعندما تحاول الان طباعة جينة،
what you do is somebody in a factory
ما يحدث هو أنه شخص ما في المصنع
with pipettes puts the thing together by hand,
باستعمال ماصات يقوم بضمها بيديه
you have one error per 100 base pairs,
يمكن أن تقوم بخطأ من 100 زوج قاعدي
and it takes a long time and costs a lot of money.
ويتطلب الكثير من الوقت كما أن تكلفته مرتفعة.
This new device
هذا الجهاز الجديد
assembles genes on a chip,
يقوم بتجميع الجينات على رقاقة
and instead of one error per 100 base pairs,
وبدلا من وقوع خطأ من 100 زوج قاعدي
it's one error per 10,000 base pairs.
فانها تصبح خطأ من 10.000 زوج قاعدي
In this lab, we will have the world's capacity
في هذا المختبر، سنملك قدرة عالمية
of gene printing within a year,
في طباعة الجينات في مدة لا تتعدى السنة،
200 million base pairs a year.
200 مليون زوج قاعدي في السنة،
This is kind of like when we went
هذا يشبه عند تغييرنا
from transistor radios wrapped by hand
من أجهزة الراديو الترانزستور ملفوفة باليد
to the Pentium.
إلى البانتيوم.
This is going to become the Pentium of bioengineering,
هذا يشبه البانتيوم بالنسبة للهندسة الحيوية
of dorm rooms and startup companies.
المساكن والشركات الناشئة.
So it's happening in software and in hardware
هكذا يحدث في البرمجيات والأجهزة
and bioengineering,
و الهندسة الحيوية
and so this is a fundamental new way of thinking about innovation.
كما أن هذا طريق أساسي جديد للتفكير في الابتكار
It's a bottom-up innovation, it's democratic,
هو الابتكار من أسفل إلى أعلى وهو الديمقراطية،
it's chaotic, it's hard to control.
وهو الفوضى، يصعب فرض السيطرة عليه.
It's not bad, but it's very different,
ليس سيئا، ولكن أنه مختلف جدا،
and I think that the traditional rules that we have
و أعتقد أن القواعد التقليدية التي نعرفها
for institutions don't work anymore,
لا تعمل بعد الآن بالنسبة للشركات
and most of us here
ومعظم الموجودين هنا
operate with a different set of principles.
يعتمد مجموعة مختلفة من المبادئ
One of my favorite principles is the power of pull,
يعتبر مبدأ قوة الجذب واحدا من المبادئ المفضلة لديّ
which is the idea of pulling resources
والذي يقوم على جذب المصادر نحوك
from the network as you need them
من الشبكة مثلما تحتاج إليها
rather than stocking them in the center
بدلا من تخزينهم في مركز
and controlling everything.
و السيطرة كل شيء.
So in the case of the Safecast story,
في حالة من القصة "Safecast"،
I didn't know anything when the earthquake happened,
لا أعرف شيئا عند وقوع الزلزال،
but I was able to find Sean
ولكن تمكنت من العثور على شون
who was the hackerspace community organizer,
الذي كان منظم مجتمع المتسللين
and Peter, the analog hardware hacker
وبيتر، متسلل الأجهزة التناظرية
who made our first Geiger counter,
الذي قام بصنع أول عداد جيجر،
and Dan, who built the Three Mile Island
ودان الذي قام ببناء نظام المراقبة
monitoring system after the Three Mile Island meltdown.
جزيرة الثلاثة أميال وذلك بعد انهيارها
And these people I wouldn't have been able to find
ولم أكن قادرا على العثور عليهم
beforehand and probably were better
من قبل، وأعتقد أنه من الجيد
that I found them just in time from the network.
أنني عثرت عليهم في الوقت المناسب من خلال الشبكة.
I'm a three-time college dropout,
تركت دراستي الجامعية ثلاث مرات،
so learning over education
لذلك يعتبر التعلّم مقارنة بالتعليم
is very near and dear to my heart,
قريبا من قلبي ومهما،
but to me, education is what people do to you
ولكن في نظري، التعليم هو يفعله الناس لك
and learning is what you do to yourself.
أما التعلّم هو ما تفعله لنفسك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And it feels like, and I'm biased,
ويبدو الأمر وكأن، وأنا منحاز لذلك،
it feels like they're trying to make you memorize
يبدو وكأنهم يريدونك أن تحفظ
the whole encyclopedia before they let you go out and play,
الموسوعة بأكملها قبل خروجك للّعب
and to me, I've got Wikipedia on my cell phone,
وبالنسبة لي، قمت بتحميل ويكيبيديا في هاتفي
and it feels like they assume
ويبدو وكأنهم يعتقدون أنك
you're going to be on top of some mountain
ستكون على قمة أحد الجبال
all by yourself with a number 2 pencil
لوحدك مع قلم رصاص رقم 2
trying to figure out what to do
تحاول معرفة ما يجب أن تقوم به،
when in fact you're always going to be connected,
عندما تكون في الحقيقة مرتبطا بالانترنت
you're always going to have friends,
سيكون عندك أصدقاء دائما،
and you can pull Wikipedia up whenever you need it,
واستخدام ويكيبيديا عندما تحتاج ذلك
and what you need to learn is how to learn.
وما تحتاج تعلمه هو كيف تتعلم؟
In the case of Safecast, a bunch of amateurs
في حالة "safecast" كنا مجموعة من الهواة
when we started three years ago,
عندما بدأنا منذ ثلاثة سنوات،
I would argue that we probably as a group
وأود أن أناقش فكرة أننا كمجموعة
know more than any other organization
كنا نعرف أكثر من أي منظمة
about how to collect data and publish data
حول كيفية جمع البيانات ونشرها
and do citizen science.
واعلام المواطن.
Compass over maps.
بوصلة مقارنة بالخريطة.
So this one, the idea is that the cost of writing a plan
بالنسبة لهذه، تقوم فكرة على أن تكلفة كتابة خطة
or mapping something is getting so expensive
أو رسم خرائط أصبح شيئا مكلفا جدا
and it's not very accurate or useful.
و ليس دقيقا أو مفيدا
So in the Safecast story, we knew we needed to collect data,
في قصة "Safecast" نعرف أننا بحاجة لجمع البيانات،
we knew we wanted to publish the data,
نعرف أننا نريد نشر البيانات
and instead of trying to come up with the exact plan,
و بدلا من محاولة لوضع خطة دقيقة
we first said, oh, let's get Geiger counters.
أقترحنا الحصول على عدادات جيجر.
Oh, they've run out.
اوه، لقد نفذت.
Let's build them. There aren't enough sensors.
لنقم بصنعها، لا يوجد ما يكفي من أجهزة الاستشعار
Okay, then we can make a mobile Geiger counter.
حسنا، إذن يمكننا صنع عداد جيجر محمول
We can drive around. We can get volunteers.
يمكننا التنقل، يمكننا الحصول على متطوعين.
We don't have enough money. Let's Kickstarter it.
لا نملك المال الكافي، لنحصل على تمويل.
We could not have planned this whole thing,
لم نكن لنستطيع التخطيط لكل شيء
but by having a very strong compass,
ولكن بامتلاكنا لبوصلة قوية،
we eventually got to where we were going,
وصلنا في نهاية المطاف إلى أين سنذهب
and to me it's very similar to agile software development,
وفي نظري هذا مماثل لتطوير البرمجيات أجيل
but this idea of compasses is very important.
ولكن هذه الفكرة عن البوصلات مهمة جدا.
So I think the good news is
بالتالي أعتقد أن الخبر الجيد
that even though the world is extremely complex,
أنه بالرغم من أن العالم معقد للغاية،
what you need to do is very simple.
ما يجب عليك القيام به بسيط جدا.
I think it's about stopping this notion
أعتقد أنه حول تخليك عن فكرة
that you need to plan everything,
أنك بحاجة أن تخططّ لكلّ شيء.
you need to stock everything,
يجب أن تقوم بتخزين كل شيء،
and you need to be so prepared,
وأن تكون مستعدا
and focus on being connected,
كما يجب أن تكون مرتبطا بالعالم
always learning,
تعلم دائما،
fully aware,
تملك الوعي التام
and super present.
ودائما موجودا وحاضرا.
So I don't like the word "futurist."
بالتالي لا تتعلق بكلمة "مستقبلي"
I think we should be now-ists,
أعتقد أنك يجب أن تعيش الحاضر،
like we are right now.
مثلما عليه نحن الآن
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)